Alright, how do you translate a movie title?
电影标题该如何翻译？
"The Texas Chain Saw Massacre"
《The Texas Chain Saw Massacre》
Let's take that as an example
以它为例
Well, you can always translate it word by word
逐字翻译试试看
But then you hit the word massacre
翻到最后一词，“massacre”
And no matter what synonym you use
你会发现，无论怎么翻译
It's bringing up connotations that... shouldn't be there
都会让人联想起……不太好的事情
So you fudge the title a bit
这时候，就只能用别的词了
Ah yes, "Texas Chain Saw Homocidal Maniac"
啊哈，《德州电锯杀人狂》
It tells you precisely the genre, the character, and the tone
准确反映出电影的类型、角色和气氛
That's the level of intricacies you have to deal with
这就是翻译标题的难度所在
Taking history, culture
历史、文化
And a whole bunch of other language-specific things into consideration
语气语境等等众多事情都需兼顾
Chinese translation is especially annoying
中文翻译尤其麻烦
Not just because of how different these two languages work
一方面是因为中英之间语法差距甚大
But because there are no less than 3 different Chinese speaking film industries
但更重要的是，中文地区有三个不同的电影圈
Four if you count Singapore
算上新加坡就有四个
Sometimes, these markets can agree on a translation
这几个地区偶尔能统一翻译
But more often than not... they don't
但大部分情况下都是各走各路
Yeah, they all mean the same thing
看，这几个标题其实都一个意思
Just different wordings
措辞不同而已
But this situation also gives us a treasure trove of titles we can compare and contrast
但这也给我们一个探索各种翻译方式的大好机会
So... let's do just that!
我们就来聊聊这个吧
Broadly speaking, there are four ways you can translate a title
粗略地讲，翻译标题有四个方式
The first one is "literal translation"
首当其冲，“直译”
Sticking as close to the original meaning as possble
尽可能保持原标题的字面意思
This is the simplest and safest method
这是最简单、最安全的翻译方式
Very little room for misinterpretations
误解机会较少
Which is why it's usually used on big budget blockbusters
一般冒不起风险的大片会选择直译
But just because the translation is literal
当然，虽然直译
Doesn't mean it can't be interesting
翻译还是很有发挥空间的
The 1996 horror movie Scream is translated literally by Mainland and Taiwan
96年恐怖电影《Scream》
Meaning "Screaming in fear"
在内地和台湾译作《惊声尖叫》
(They are the exact same title, by the way)
（当然，两岸有简繁之别）
(Just difference between traditional and simplified Chinese)
（这里就不过度深究这个了）
It's intentionally vague and kinda silly
译题和英文原标题一样
Just like its English title
略有喜感
Alluding to the film's self-aware tone
暗示了电影自我讽刺的内容
But Hong Kong went one step further
但是香港更有意思
You see, the last character here is a pun, meaning "call"
《夺命狂呼》的“呼”为双关
It can mean "A Deadly Call for Help", like a scream
既有”呼喊“救命之意
But also mean "A Deadly Call On the Phone"
又指电话“传呼”
Referring to the opening sequence
联系起电影开场一幕
The 2000 French Romantic Comedy Amélie is another example
2000年法国浪漫喜剧《Amélie》也是一例
Taiwan's "Amélie's Fantasy World" is actually closer to the original French Title
台湾译题《艾蜜莉的异想世界》更接近法文原题
“Le Fabuleux Destin d'Amélie Poulain”
“ Le Fabuleux Destin d'AméliePoulain”
(Yeah, I can speak French)
（对，我会说法语）
But Hong Kong and Mainland translates Amélie's name phonetically into a pun
但香港和内地将Amélie翻译成双关语
It sounds like "Angel Amélie"
念出来发音相似
But reads like "Angel Loves Beauty"
读起来却别有含义
Which is clever, because in a way
这就很高明了
The movie is about Amélie learning to love the beauty of the world
因为电影讲述着女主角学会欣赏世界的美丽
And bringing happiness to people... like an angel
并像个天使一样给人带来幸福的故事
I would give it a chef kiss
要这电影是意大利拍的
But this movie is French, not Italian
我还真想给个厨师之吻
That said, literal translation is safe but not perfect
不过，直译虽然安全，但并不完美
For one thing, you have to choose your words carefully
首先，你得仔细选择用词
Mainland China translates the Fast and Furious series as "Speed and Passion"
《Fast and Furious》系列在内地译作《速度与激情》
Sounds about right
字面上是直译
But the word they choose for passion has a slight sexual connotation these days
可是“激情”这个词在网上有点……色情的含义
It sounds kinda weird and dirty to a Chinese ear
内地观众读起来就有点怪怪的
I guess that's why there are so many homoerotic fanfics bbout the two protagonists
这大概就是系列“基情”同人文泛滥的原因吧……
Now that I think about it, maybe it's intentional...?
……难道是故意翻译成这样的吗？
And then sometimes, a title just flat out can't be translated
再有时候，英文标题根本不能直译
Tarantino's Pulp Fiction is one of those
塔伦蒂诺的《Pulp Fiction》便是一例
The "Pulp" in "Pulp Fiction" came from the type of paper used for cheap novels
《Pulp Fiction》中的Pulp指的是廉价小说用的木浆纸
These novels usually feature sex, drugs, guns and all sort of tropes
这些小说通常都描述性、毒、枪之类的边缘话题
It's a term that only really makes sense in English
这个语境和含义，只存在于英语里
Mainland translated it as "Low-Brow Novel"
内地将其翻译成《低俗小说》
The surface-level meaning is preserved, but the context is pretty much entirely lost
表面意思翻译过来，深层含义却被忽略了
Personally, I think Hong Kong's "Dangerous Personnel" best captures the vibe
个人而言，我认为香港的《危险人物》更好表达出电影的气氛
And that leads to our second way of translating a title: reinterpretation
这种时候，就需要动用第二种翻译方式：意译
Instead of translating from the English title
不直接文字翻译
This is when you come up with your own title by interpreting the plot
而是诠释电影剧情，意译新标题
It's usually a good way to deal with titles that can't be easily translated
若标题无法直译，取个新标题未尝不可
The aforementioned "Dangerous Personnel" is a good example of this
前面提到的《危险人员》就是便是好例子
Christopher Nolan's Inception is another example
诺兰的《Inception》也是一例
It's about a bunch of thieves running around people's dream where reality is distorted
故事讲述一群盗贼潜入别人的梦境
The word "Inception" sounds cool and thrilling and imposing and cerebral
英文单词“inception”充满悬疑感，气氛浩大，听起来就烧脑
An there isn't an equivalent word in Chinese
中文里却没有能直接对应的单词
Taiwan attempted a literal translation "Full-Scale Initiation"
台湾的直译《全面启动》
Which is close... but not quite there
算是比较接近，但还是差了一点
That's why Mainland and Hong Kong came up with their own titles
这就是内地和香港意译新标题的原因
Mainland calls it "Dream Theft Dimension"
内地译作《盗梦空间》
Which I think is absolutely amazing
相当出彩的翻译
Hong Kong's "Dimensional Infiltration" gives it a bit more of a spy thriller edge
香港的《潜行凶间》则更有间谍片的气氛
Matrix is another one with no equivalent words in Chinese
“Matrix”一词也不能直译
At least nothing as sci-fi and cool sounding
对应单词没有足够的科幻感
... It sounds nerdy as heck
听起来只是很宅
So instead, Taiwan and Mainland both translate it as the awesome sounding "Empire of Hackers"
所以台湾和内地将之译成《黑/骇客帝国》
Capturing the scale and the coolness factor
捕捉到了电影的气派和帅气
Hong Kong's "22nd Century Killer Network" is... less cool
香港的《廿二世纪杀人网络》……就没那么帅了……
(Yeah I don't know why they call it that)
（我也不知道为什么要这样翻译）
Hong Kong's title for The Truman Show is great, though
《The Truman Show》的香港标题倒是十分出彩
The title comes from a 24/7 reality show about the main character Truman
这电影讲述主角Truman，在不知情的情况下
Unknowingly living in a fabricated reality
一只生活在一个24小时真人秀里
Mainland and Taiwan went with the relatively safe "Truman's World"
内地台湾都选了比较直白的《楚门的世界》
Hong Kong went with "Reality Show"
香港则译作《真人Show》
But wait! it's not reality!
可是大家都是演员啊！
Exactly!
没错！
In fact, going word by word, the title literally means "A show featuring real humans"
逐字理解，标题意思是“来自真人的演出”
And the movie is about Truman
而电影将的是主角Truman
A "True Man"
一个”真实（true）的人（man）“
And how his humanity breaks him out of a fake TV reality
凭着人性对自由的向往，逃出虚假现实的故事
Spike Jonze indie sci-fi romance film, Her, talks about a geek
斯派克·琼斯的独立科幻浪漫电影，《Her》，讲述一个技术宅
Falling in love with an AI who sounds like Scarlet Johansson
和一个人工智能谈恋爱的故事
Mainland just has a direct translation
内地的翻译不能更直白
Hong Kong is a bit more poetic
香港则稍添诗意
But Taiwan completely reinterprets the title
但台湾完全重新意译了一个新名字
Calling it "Cloud-based Lover"
译作《云端情人》
Which not only hints at the technology behind the AI
既表达出了人工智能背后的科技
But also the distance between the two characters
又表达出了两位主角之间的距离
And her intangibility
以及女主角无影无形的本质
That's freaking awesome!
翻译的太棒了
Okay, one more. Because this is fun
再来一个例子，这个好玩
Inglourious Basterds
《Inglourious Basterds》
Tarantino's Nazisploitation film about a group of Jewish soldiers hunting nazis for sport
塔伦蒂诺的纳粹电影，讲述一群犹太士兵猎杀纳粹分子的架空故事
While Mainland and Taiwan gave a pretty straight-forward translation
内地和台湾的翻译比较直接
Hong Kong just GETS Tarantino
但是香港完全捕捉到了塔伦蒂诺的精髓
I swear I'm not making this up
我发誓这是真标题
"Demon Hitler"
《希魔...
"Versus Homicidal Maniacs"
撞正杀人狂》
It's ridiculous until you realize
听起来笑炸了
That's exactly the kind of movie Tarantino makes
但这确实就是塔伦蒂诺的电影风格
Nazisploitation!
纳粹邪典！
Like She Wolf of the SS, just done well and tasteful
跟《She Wolf of the SS》系列属同一类型，只是拍的很好罢了
I guess Hong Kong and Tarantino just love each other
香港和塔伦蒂诺完全就是真爱啊
Did you know Mighty Peking Man was distributed by Tarantino in the West?
你知道不？《猩猩王》的英文版是塔伦蒂诺发行的哦
Now, reinterpretation may sound great
意译标题听起来方便
But it does have at least 2 potential pitfalls
但也有两个潜在陷阱
The first one is...
第一个是......
Well, sometimes, it doesn't age well
好些时候，这些标题都不长久
The Mission Impossible series was called "Spies on a Disk" in Mainland China
内地将《The Mission Impossible》系列译作《碟中谍》
Referring to the list of spy names mcguffin in the first movie
指的是第一部里，存有间谍名单的重要光碟
But then the series continues without that thing ever showing up again
但随着系列的继续发展，这个光碟再也没有出现过
And the title just completely loses all meaning
标题的原意也就消失了
The Terminator is another example
《The Terminator》也是个好例子
Instead of using the villain's name
英文标题本是反派的名字
Hong Kong titled it after the hero's identity
香港却选择以主角的身份命题
Kyle Reese is a warrior, and he is from the future
男主角是个来自未来的战士
But then the sequels put more emphasis on the Terminators
但系列所有续集都增加了终结者的戏份
And Kyle Reese is almost entirely forgotten
第一代男主角几乎被遗忘了
The second translation pitfall is straight-up misinterpretations
意译的第二个潜在陷阱便是剧情误解
This is when the translator doesn't get the movie
就是翻译没看懂电影的情况
Manchester by the Sea is a drama about a man confronting his own path after his brother's death
《Manchester by the Sea》讲述男主哥哥去世后，不得不回到故乡处理后事的故事
Hong Kong translates it as "Love Ties to the Seaside Town"
香港将其译为《情系海边之城》
But... it's not a love story, and it doesn't have that much to do with love
可是……这不是爱情故事，也没有什么亲情可言
It puts the movie in a genre it doesn't belong
标题直接把电影给错误归类了
Contact is another one
《Contact》也是类似情况
It's about an astronomer trying to contact alien life
电影里，一位天文学家在试图联系外星人的同时
While also dealing with her past trauma
要学会处理了她过去的创伤
So the Taiwanese title "Contact the Future"
台湾译题《接触未来》
Is kinda the polar opposite of what the astronomer is doing
就和主角的故事截然相反了
She isn't really reaching to the future as much as she's freeing herself from the past
她并不要去未来，她的目标是放开过去
If you are planning on reinterpreting the movie title
要想意译标题
You better be sure you have a firm understanding of the movie
就必须要对电影有足够深度理解才行
Onto the third way of translating: poetic translation
接下来是第三种翻译方式：归化
This is when you incorporate cultural context from the Chinese language into your translation
就是利用本地文化来诠释标题的深层含义
Kubrick's Lolita is a good example of this
库布里克的《Lolita》便是有名字里
A movie about a man's inappropriate obsession with an underage girl
电影讲述一个男人对一位未成年少女有非分之想的故事
The original book has a phonetically translated title in all three regions
《Lolita》原书在两岸三地本都是音译
But when the movie got released
但电影上映时
Hong Kong and Taiwan got a bit... cheeky with the title
港台两地就有点俏皮了
It reads "A Pear Tree Crushing a Begonia"
译作《一树梨花压海棠》
Which came from a famous poem written to mock old men who marry young women
为中国民间诗句，用于嘲讽老来纳妾之人
It's beautiful on the surface
字面上很浪漫
But a "big yikes" when you think about it
仔细想想却让人毛骨悚然
So, a perfect fit for this movie
完美诠释电影潜台词
Another similar example would be "Knives Out"
再一例子：《Knives Out》
A murder mystery filled with tension
一部充满悬念的侦探电影
Both Mainland and Taiwan chose existing idioms for their title
内地和台湾都以成语为标题
Mainland chose "Sharp Blade Unsheathed"
内地译作《利刃出鞘》
Meaning tension is high, people are one step away from killing each other
指气氛紧张，杀人见血，一触即发
Taiwan chose "Blades Curved And Roads Turned"
台湾则译作《锋回路转》
Meaning the story has taken an unexpected turn
意指剧情曲折离奇
Both titles reference the knives motif
两个标题都提及了片中的刀刃主题
But also gives additional context through cultural references
同时也通过本地文化去进一步诠释电影
Now, you don't always have to be classy, either
归化翻译也不一定要很文雅
Sharknado-
《Sharknado》
Yes, Sharknado, a movie about sharks flying in a tornado
对，《Sharknado》，一部关于鲨鱼在龙卷风里飞来飞去的电影
Has one of the most poetic and funny Chinese titles I've ever seen
有着我见过最搞笑又最有诗意的中文译题
In Chinese, tornado is called "Dragon twisting wind"
龙卷风这个词，本来就有动物
Naturally, mainland and Hong Kong replaced one of the words with shark
自然，内地和香港直接以“鲨”字取代一字
And it works
简单有效
But Taiwan hilariously referenced a classic pop song
但台湾很俏皮地引用了一首台语流行曲
In which the lyrics describe a romantic image of the desert sands dancing in the wind
曲中歌词描述着边疆沙漠风飞沙舞的浪漫画面
And since the words "sand" and "shark" are homonyms...
而“沙”和“鲨”又同音
Well, now a hilarious mental image is stuck in your head
一下子画面感就出来了
Genius.
真天才
Of course, like other methods
当然，和其他方式一样
Poetic translations can go wrong
归化也有翻译错误的可能
Disney's Coco is a movie about a kid traveling the world of the dead , trying to find his musical idol
迪斯尼的《Coco》讲述一个小孩在亡者世界寻找偶像的故事
Mainland's "Dream Chase Odyssey", good translation
内地的《寻梦环游记》，好翻译
Taiwan's "Coco's Nightclub"... not so much
台湾的《可可夜总会》……就有点怪怪的了
Okay, "nightclub" is a Taiwanese euphemism for "cemetery"
在台湾，“夜总会”是墓地的别称
So, it KINDA cleverly alludes to the musical theme, the theme of death, and the dazzling lights
所以这个标题其实联系到了电影的音乐主题、死亡主题，还有光影主题
But all that subtext is useless
虽然潜台词很棒
When the surface level text is more or less entirely out of whack
表面含义却完全没有贴合儿童电影的定位
This is the definition of trying way too hard
这就是典型的用力过度啊
Another seemingly beautiful one is Slumdog Millionaire
另一个乍看很浪漫的标题，《Slumdog Millionaire》
A movie about a young man going on "Who Wants to Be a Millionaire"
电影讲述了一个年轻人参加《百万富翁》
And through the show, he reconnects with his childhood love
并通过节目，找回了他失散多年的童年之爱
Hong Kong gave it a very poetic title "One Million And One Nights"
香港取了一个非常浪漫的标题《一百万零一夜》
It references the "Who Wants to Be a Millionaire" game show
提及了《百万富翁》游戏节目
It's also a metaphor for the length of time
又比喻到了主角等了很长时间
the main character waited to meet his love again
终于找回爱情的感觉
It also feels like a fairytale
而且标题充满童话感
Because it references the book "One Thousand and One Night"
引用了《一千零一夜》
Which... It's an Arabian book
来自阿拉伯地区的名著……
This movie is set in INDIA!
电影故事设定在印度！
God damn it, Hong Kong...
香港啊……
Last, and also maybe the least exciting way
最后，也是最无聊的翻译方式
There is the marketing translation
营销翻译
This is when a title is fudged to make the movie more marketable
就是为了让电影更卖座而对标题进行修改
A basic example would be 1994's "Speed"
1994年的《Speed》便是典型例子
A movie about a bus that explodes if it drives too slow
讲述一辆开得太慢就会爆炸的巴士的电影
With a generic-sounding title like Speed
《Speed》，就是《时速》这个标题并没有什么特点
Hong Kong added a word to signal its genre: "Speed of Life and Death"
于是香港便加上“生死”一字，增加电影的紧张刺激感
And since Chinese is such a compact language
中文字少意深
You can usually get away with more complicated titles
标题也就相应能复杂一点
Taiwan is especially fond of this types of marketing translation
台湾尤其喜欢这种营销翻译
Speed becomes "Police Protector"
《Speed》变成《捍卫战警》
Top Gun becomes "Warrior Protector"
《Top Gun》变成《捍卫战士》
And John Wick becomes "Mission to Protect"
《John Wick》变成《捍卫任务》
The most infamous example is probably "Shawshank Redemption"
提到这个就不得不提到《Shawshank Redemption》
To which Taiwan gave it a nonsensical translation of...
台湾的翻译经常被人诟病
(And I did not make this up)
（前方高能）
"Excitement 1995"
《刺激1995》
Okay, let me explain
好吧，我解释一下
When Shawshank first came out in the US, it was a box office bomb
《Shawshank Redemption》在美国上映之初，票房惨淡
And with a nondescript title like that, I can see why
这个没什么特色的标题，估计是原因之一
So, the Taiwanese distributor marketed it as
于是台湾方面决定把这部电影
A spiritual successor to the 1973 movie "The Sting"
卖成1973年电影《The Sting》的精神续作
Which was called "Excitement" in Taiwan
《The Sting》在台湾翻译成《刺激》
"Excitment"
《刺激》
"Excitment 1995"
《刺激1995》
And, as far as I know, the strategy worked!
而据我所知，这个策略确实奏效
It made box office record in Taiwan
电影在台湾创了票房记录
So you may laugh at this, but Taiwan got it to work!
所以，你笑归笑，台湾发行商笑得比你开心
This strategy is used for many Arnold movies, too
施瓦辛格电影在台湾也有类似处理
They are marketed as the "Demon" series in Taiwan
他很多电影都被归类成《魔鬼》系列
"Demon Terminator"
《魔鬼终结者》
"Demon Commando"
《魔鬼司令》
"Demon Emperor: True Lies"
《魔鬼大帝：真实谎言》
"Demon Jr."
《魔鬼二世》
It's funny, but it works
很搞笑，但很奏效
Of course, it's not a exclusively a Taiwanese thing
当然，也不只有台湾会这样做
A lot of the Pixar movies are also like this in Mainland
皮克斯很多电影在内地也是系列化处理
Toys Mobilized
《玩具总动员》
Undersea Mobilized
《海底总动员》
Racing Cars Mobilized
《赛车总动员》
Superheros Mobilized
《超人总动员》
Hong Kong has a similar shtick going on, too
香港也有类似处理，成为《奇兵》系列
By now, you can already see the major problem with this method
我想大家都注意到这个翻译方式的最大问题
It's mind-numbingly boring
实在太太太没创意了
Se7en, a detective thriller about a serial murderer in the theme of the seven deadly sins is called
《Se7en》，一部讲述以七宗罪为主题的连环谋杀案电影
"Flash Point Warrant"
在台湾叫《火线追缉令》
It conveys none of the mysteries and style of the movie
完全没有表达出电影风格
It sounds more like Donnie Yen is about to kick some ass
听起来更像是甄子丹要打架
Shyamalan's Unbreakable is called "Tribulations of the Undying" in Mainland
沙马兰的《Unbreakable》在内地译作《不死劫》
A poetic way to describe the main character
描述出了主角
A man who has above average physique that makes him a real-life superhero
因体魄异于常人，成为超级英雄的故事
Taiwan just calls it...
台湾则译作……
"Thrilling"...
《惊心动魄》
I have no idea why!
就没点创意吗！？
So, that's four ways of translating a movie title into another language
以上就是四种翻译标题的方法啦
Let's see...
一起看看
There's "the direct translation"
有“直译”
The safe but not always possible option
相对安全，但不一定能找到对应词语
"Reinterpretation"
“意译”
A good option to bring in some personality
译者可以更自由地诠释电影
But you have to make sure you understand the film well enough
但你要确保自己对电影理解无误
"The poetic translation"
“归化”
Bringing in cultural references to provide additional context
引入本地文化以更完美表达语境
And "the marketing translation"
还有“营销翻译”
Boring, but it works
无聊，但有效
Of course, these options are not mutually exclusive
当然了，这四个方法互相并不冲突
And it's generally ideal if you can achieve more than one at a time
能一次达到多个目的自然上好
But like all art forms, there is no definitive way to do it right
但和其他艺术形式一样，没有哪一种方式是万能的
That's also what makes this topic so much fun to look into
但这也是标题翻译的趣味所在
Have you paid attention to any movie titles lately?
你最近有没有注意到哪些有趣的标题呢？
Take a look next time
注意看看吧
You might be surprised by the amount of thought that goes into it
背后的涵义，可能会让你大吃一惊
So... Yeah.
就这样吧